<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Eight-Fingered Atom]]></title>
  <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-24T08:17:19-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Alan Fung-Schwarz]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to install Rails on Ubuntu using rbenv]]></title>
    <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/11/27/how-to-install-rails-on-ubuntu-using-rbenv/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-27T20:31:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/11/27/how-to-install-rails-on-ubuntu-using-rbenv</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first step is to follow this great write-up on Gist from (https://gist.github.com/2627011)[Olistik].</p>

<h3>Get rbenv</h3>

<pre><code>cd ~
git clone git://github.com/sstephenson/rbenv.git .rbenv
echo 'export PATH="$HOME/.rbenv/bin:$PATH"' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
echo 'eval "$(rbenv init -)"' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
exec $SHELL
</code></pre>

<h3>Get ruby-build</h3>

<pre><code>mkdir -p ~/.rbenv/plugins
cd ~/.rbenv/plugins
git clone git://github.com/sstephenson/ruby-build.git
echo 'export PATH="$HOME/.rbenv/plugins/ruby-build/bin:$PATH"' &gt;&gt; ~/.bashrc
exec $SHELL
</code></pre>

<h3>Get ruby</h3>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install zlib1g-dev build-essential libssl-dev libreadline-dev
rbenv install 1.9.3-p327
rbenv global 1.9.3-p327
</code></pre>

<h3>Set local version</h3>

<p>Go into the directory containing your Rails app</p>

<pre><code>rbenv local 1.9.3-p327
</code></pre>

<p>It will create a .rbenv-version file to ensure that you switch to the right ruby version
in case you decide to upgrade.</p>

<h3>Disable installation of rdoc and ri</h3>

<pre><code>echo "gem: --no-ri --no-rdoc" &gt; ~/.gemrc
</code></pre>

<h3>Install dependencies for nokogiri and postgresql</h3>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install libxml2-dev libxslt1-dev postgresql libpq-dev
</code></pre>

<h3>Install bundler and bundle install</h3>

<pre><code>gem install bundler
bundle install
</code></pre>

<h3>Set up Postgres</h3>

<pre><code>sudo -u postgres psql # and in the postgres type the following with the appropriate substitution
create user username with createdb password strong_password;
create database rails_devel with owner username;
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[To try]]></title>
    <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/10/22/the-to-try/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T22:03:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/10/22/the-to-try</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I watched the last twenty minutes of the debate after I came home.
This came after a day at work where I felt lost and unproductive.</p>

<p>&#8220;Welcome to the developer&#8217;s life,&#8221; said my boss, when I responded haltingly
of how finished the models were. I said that I was finished and not finished.</p>

<p>I don&#8217;t know how it is that I know and do not know. I feel as if my brain
is trying to slither—without a muscle—around some sharp right-angle
corner, a line drawing on a graph paper.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I am an intern]]></title>
    <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/18/i-am-an-intern/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-18T12:59:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/18/i-am-an-intern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was an intern once, for something I didn&#8217;t regard as particularly
useful. I spent 200 hours, divided into segment of four-hour period,
working on the farm, where I helped a former plant biologist
transplant seedlings from a small pot of soil to a bigger pot.
They are then placed in the farmland, and they are grown organically,
using drop irrigation to avoid wasting water, in Sunol.
For the effort, I received something like $200. It was a fantastic
experience, and almost gave me a green thumb. Almost. Alas, after the
internship was over, my plant-growing ability has not improved at all,
nor has my interest ever burgeoned into an obsession or a routine &#8212;
I have not watered any plant lately.</p>

<p>I am an intern again, for a different field entirely, and I am excited.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[8:30 to 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/08/8-30-to-5/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-08T19:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/08/8-30-to-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I used to have a 8:30 &#8211; 17:00 job, but I quit after 101th day, nine months
later. If you calculate it, you will know that I worked 12
days a month or less. It was also an $11/hour job, and I needed to commute 50+
miles round trip.</p>

<p>It took me a long time to leave, and I had to have a combination of factors
convincing me, which I will first list then explain:</p>

<ol>
<li>Gasoline.</li>
<li>Nothing new to learn.</li>
<li>Learning Ruby programming during my off days.</li>
<li>Finding a job posting from a deaf-owned company looking for a
Ruby developer.</li>
<li>Being more confident about my future job prospect.</li>
</ol>


<p>I drove 250 miles a week three weeks a month (including going to Berkeley
for aikido practice) and earned per week not much more than $352 and as low as $230.</p>

<p>How can I be willing to spend $45 a week for gas out of so small an income.
I worked there so long because it was my first job and I was happy
to even be able to find work. I still feel deeply appreciative to them for
being willing to hire me even though I was probably the farthest temp commuter
to have accepted the job offer.</p>

<p>Still, despite working there, I always had the sense that I wouldn&#8217;t stay there
for long. The first reason was that the job didn&#8217;t require my level of education.
I also always did the same thing every day: open boxes
in the morning, sort specimens, sometimes do data entry, and otherwise
do filtering the rest of the day (consisting of pouring urine aliquot, taking
out fibrin and putting a filter in, and centrifugation).
I learned some data entry for a limited set of requisitions, but they didn&#8217;t
teach me any more.</p>

<p>For three months, I focused on doing my job, thinking that it would be too early
to consider applying to other jobs. The first month was hard, and
I was glad to have a break, in which I recovered. It got easier later,
when I then could use my break weeks to learn more programming. I didn&#8217;t think
of anything else I could do, except retail, writing and social work.</p>

<p>It is a mark of my limited range when I say that I literally could not think
of what kind of job I wanted, only that I studied for either working in the
laboratories and was studying what I was interested in.</p>

<p>Months before working at Spectra, I started the <a href="http://ruby.learncodethehardway.com">Learn Ruby the Hard Way</a>.
I also read through Why the Lucky Stiff, and I was trying to challenge myself,
almost deciding on a career change since I was likely not going to succeed.
Will Johansson&#8217;s saying that he only knew <code>10.times { print "Hello World!" }</code>
convinced me to learn because I kind of wanted a language unused by him.
During the weeks I had no work, I focused on trying to learn the programming
language, even though I had my doubt because I wasn&#8217;t the nerd or geek
who started writing scripts at the age of 12. Don&#8217;t I have to be &#8220;that guy&#8221;
in order to be a real programmer?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>That high standard was sometimes the obstacle, sometimes the motivation.</p>

<p>I took Statistics followed by Computational Intelligence
at UC Santa Cruz Silicon Valley Extension, in the hope that both would
give me a solid background for bioinformatics, which was a field I was interested
in even though all the job postings seemed to want a PhD. I didn&#8217;t really
see much hope for me, but stayed patient.</p>

<p>One day, I decided to look on Craigslist for any listing mentioning &#8220;deaf.&#8221;
Usually I see only a few listing involving working with deaf people. That day,
there was a posting for &#8220;Ruby Developer.&#8221; Piqued, I took a look.</p>

<p>They were looking for
someone who could program using Backbone.js, EventMachine, etc. They used the word
&#8220;mandatory&#8221;, which made me feel like I wasn&#8217;t qualified for it.
Thinking retrospectively, I realized
that the posting was simply trying to be clear about its
requirements. No sense in using buzzwords like Web 2.0 and Big Data
when you are looking for a specific job to get done. Moreover, they were
also open to internships, so clearly plenty of little tasks even if I couldn&#8217;t
do the EventMachine or Backbone thing.</p>

<p>I didn&#8217;t want to apply at first, but I was indeed very curious what it might be,
whether there was ambiguity in them saying that I would be working with a
deaf-owned company. I saw two possible meanings: That it was a hearing company
that had contract work with a deaf company; that it was a company owned by
deaf people.</p>

<p>Nate encouraged me to apply. I decided to go for it, following his advice
of being upfront about my lack of experience,
giving a short life story (growing up deaf
in an oralist environment, learning ASL, being able to communicate).
Cognizant of how some well-known developers have complained about
Computer Science Departments all across the country graduating people
who absolutely didn&#8217;t know how to code, who couldn&#8217;t answer an interview
question regarding how to write a certain function (like FizzBuzz), I wrote
saying that I could write FizzBuzz in several
different ways.</p>

<p>They replied saying they wanted to interview me. The interview was quite
interesting, all conducted in sign language. Unlike other interviews, where
I have an interpreter and usually talk, this was an interview in which I
completely sign. The questions two of three people in the room
asked came across as being easy
on me, while the third person asked challenging questions like whether
I knew WEBRick, and how to implement a chat server. I was heartened
when one of the others said that even he couldn&#8217;t think of how to answer
that question, so I somewhat understood it to be a joke.</p>

<p>I still think back on it with a kind of relief and joy.</p>

<p>Then they said they would contact me later. That was a brief period of
uncertainty where I emailed them and they didn&#8217;t reply (I&#8217;m insecure like that)
but it turned out to be just someone feeling ill and another going out of town.</p>

<p>I wrote the code they needed. Then a month later, despite not knowing
whether I would be able to stay in the compnay, I sent an email to say that I
quit. People congratulated me at Spectra, which probably means that they
expected me to leave, just like they expect every other temp to leave.</p>

<p>I&#8217;m happy.</p>

<p>I haven&#8217;t gotten any money yet, but I&#8217;m happy. I want to say it changed my life,
but that wouldn&#8217;t be totally accurate because the change was limited to quitting
my job. Once I get an income, I&#8217;d be rather glad.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Setting up another blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/07/setting-up-another-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-07T14:56:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://alanjcfs.github.com/blog/2012/09/07/setting-up-another-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have set up another blog after I found that Jekyll Bootstrap was stagnant.
Of course, ideally a framework should hardly change, but I feel more confident
about Octopress for being the work of multiple programmers than about
Bootstrap, which has been left behind by its creator in favor of creating a
language-agnostic blogging platform. I will attempt move some stuff from
the old framework to the new.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
